Guide to the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg, History, 1963-2018 UPG.RG.00
ULS Greensburg
University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg, History
1963-2018
ULS Greensburg
University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg
UPG.RG.00
7 boxes
History of the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg, 1963-2018
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Custodial History
Transferred from the Office of the President to the UPG Archives.
Scope and Content Notes
History,1963-2018, General Information, Organizational Chart, Anniversaries, Capital Fund Campaign, Certificates, Directories, Handbooks, Policy Statements, Proclamation
See Also
Note: For Additional Historical Information:
See also: RG61 C.14, Audio Cassette of "Tour of Lynch Hall" by Dr. Albert Smith, Sept. 28, 1986; RG61 C.15, Audio Cassette of "Interview with Kathryn Lynch", August 1986; RG61 C.16, Audio Cassette of "Interview with Thomas Lynch", July 22, 1986; RG61 C.17, Audio Cassette of "Interview with John and Anne Kickler, July 22, 1986 [JK UPG Gardener and Chauffeur to the Lynch Family].
RG60 Video Cassette. VC I. Campus History (VC 1-3, 4a-4g, 5) See also: RG02.4 Ser.: Publications. We Made No Small Plans: A Memior by Dr. Frank A. Cassell. See also: RG02.4 Ser.: Resource File For We Made No Small Plans: A Memoir.
See also: RG02.4 Ser.: Album. A Decade of Investing in Excellence. President Frank A. Cassell. University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg. 1997-2007.
Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Greensburg -- Records and correspondence; University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg
- General Information, August 24, 2006; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  UPG Campus Mailing Address changed from 1150 Mt. Pleasant Road, Greensburg, Pa. 15601-5898 to 150 Finoli Drive, Greensburg, Pa. 15601-5898 in Aug. 2006. [Memo. 8/24/06 from Joyce Bucchi]
  - General Information, August 24, 2006 (File-cabinet 1, Drawer 1, Box 1)
- Organizational Chart, 1995-2007; II.
  1995, October
  1999, January 20
  1999, July 31
  2000, August 8
  2007, July
  See Also
  n.b. As of Feb., 2016, no new organizational charts issued since 2007. For organizational and administrative changes, see RG02.1, 02.2, 02.3, 02.4, 02.5 Ser.: Memoranda, and RG05 Principals. Ser.: Memoranda.) faz 2/25/2016
  [See also: RG00 Ser.: Faculty/Staff Directory for other Organizational Charts.]
  - Organizational Chart, 1995-2007 (File-cabinet 1, Drawer 1, Box 1)
- Anniversaries, 1988; III.
  - 25th Anniversary, 1988; 1.
    Proclamation, County of Westmoreland, Board of County Commissioners 8 September 1988.
    Citation, Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, House of Representatives. 22 August 1988
    on the 25th Anniversary of the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg.
    Congratulations, Senate of Pennsylvania, July 6, 1988 on the 25th Anniversary of the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg.
    Commemorative Paperweight See: UPG Archives RG69 Artifacts.
    - 25th Anniversary, 1988 (File-cabinet 1, Drawer 1, Box 1)
  - 40th Anniversary, 2003; 2.
    Certificates, Citations, Proclamations Contains: Citation, "Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, House of Representatives on the 40th Anniversary of the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg" sponsored by the Hon. Thomas Tangretti, Sept. 5, 2003; "Senate of Pennsylvania Congratulations [on 40th Anniversary]" sponsored by Sen. Allen G. Kukovich and dtd Sept. 17, 2003; "Certificate of Recognition to the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg on its 40th Anniversary" from Sen. Allen G. Kukovich 39th Senatorial District of Pennsylvania, Sept. 11, 2003; [Certificate of Recognition of the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg 40th Anniversary" sponsored by Timothy F. Murphy, Member of Congress, 18th Cong. District and dtd Dec. 4, 2003].
    UPG Chronology, 1963-2003 Includes "Chronology UPG 1963-2003" prepared by the UPG Archives; "A Brief History of the University of the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg 1963-2003: Forty Years of Change and Continuity" (gives lists: UPG Presidents; President's Medal for Distinguished Service Award Recipients; UPG Commencement Speakers; Chancellor's Distinguished Teaching Award Winners; Pitt-Greensburg Alumni Assoc, Distinguished Alumni Award Winners; "UPG and the Community"; "Students and Student Life"; "Alumni Activities"; "A Beautiful 219 Acre Four-year Campus"; "Forty Years Ago"); a print copy of the UPG 40th Anniversary web site: 3 components – "The Beginning, 1963-1980", "The Transition, 1980-1997", "The Present, 1997-2003".
    UPG 40th Anniversary Events Overview Includes: preliminary ideas (prior to March 2002); plan for the celebration 9/03-5/04; plan for 9/4/03 reception; events list 9/26/03-4/24/04; tentative calendar of events 6/03-4/04; opening celebration attendees list; 9/11/03 kick off event plan plus program; media releases.
    UPG 40th Anniversary Committee File, Feb. 2002-Apr. 2004 Includes: memoranda/correspondence between committee members in re: early planning of 40th anniversary events (preliminary ideas); minutes of meetings (organization of academic participation chart; development of 40th anniversary web site; event development for anniversary; flag pole cost quote; "Wall of Honor" idea and development); also includes: 40th anniversary logo development; first "40 years of UPG History" draft - "The End of the Beginning"; correspondence with Chancellor Nordenberg and Provost Maher about attendance at Sept. 11th kick off event from Dr. Cassell; memorandum from FAC in re end of 40th anniversary events/celebration.
    Subject Files
    Banners, Display Boards, Logo Contains text for Banner and Display Boards; Banners: University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg Presidents, 1962-2003; Advisory Board, University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg, 1963; Corporations and Businesses; Foundations; Chancellor's Distinguished Teaching and Service Awardees [1986-2002]; President's Medal for Distinguished Service Award Recipients, 1998-2003; Da Vinci Society Scholars, 2002-2003; Scholarships; PGAA Outstanding Faculty and Distinguished Alumni Awardee (Outstanding Faculty, 2001-2003); Distinguished Alumni [awarded 2002-2003]; "To All of the Friends of UPG We Say: Merci, Siyabonga, Danke, Grazie, Jollaktom, Gracias, Nandi, Doh je; Arigato, Wa'-do, Thank you." [Note: UPG Archives holds the actual banners which are in circular tubes]. Display Boards Text: Academic Villages; Academics; Alumni; Athletics; Community Service; The Conference Place; International Study; Smart Growth [Smart Growth Partnership of Westmoreland Co.]; The UPG Campus; Westmoreland Heritage. File folder also contains material on the UPG 40th Anniversary logo.
    Budget (UPG 40th Anniversary Program) Level sheets: 3/13/03, 5/20/03
    Capitol Steps General File: includes correspondence and memoranda (3/30/04-4/8/04); Capitol Steps Introduction; Program; Invitation to Reception to Join the Cast after the performance; Expenditures/Revenue of Capitol Steps Program.
    Contract: includes contract; Capitol Steps Out-of-town Production specifications; Care and Feeding of your Capitol Steps Show.
    Promotional Materials (includes packet of Public Relations materials; brief video cassette.
    Publicity: includes promotional material prepared by UPG University Relations and Institutional Advancement; ticket order information; newspaper clippings.
    Visual Images: See RG60 Visual Images. Prints. Capitol Steps; See RG60 Visual Images Video Cassette VC VII.23.
    Poster: See qRG52 Subject File. Ser.: UPG President's Scholarship Fund. [Housed in Map Case]
    Events Contains program for UPG vs UPB Women's and Men's Basketball Game for the Rose Trophy. Petersen Events Center (Oakland Campus), Saturday, Jan. 31, 2004; 40th Anniversary UPG Commencement Program, 4/24/04.
    Flyers/Handouts for UPG 40th Anniversary Celebration.
    Invitation Includes: printed invitation "to join us for a program and reception opening a year-long celebration of the 40th Anniversary of the Partnership between the University of Pittsburgh and Westmoreland County", Thursday, 9/11/2003, Ferguson Theater, Smith Hall, UPG; Original List "40th Anniversary Attendees" [n.b. This list reflects those who indicated that they were going to attend. Some on this list did not attend as they had indicated while others not on the list were in attendance. per Dolly Biskup via Karen Gavula. faz.]
    Library Display Material Display materials for 40th UPG Anniversary. For oversize display material, RG00 History Ser.: 40th Anniversary 2003 [Housed in Map Case]
    Memorabilia Contains: 2 framed miniature prints, an exact size reproduction of an original color painting of Lynch Hall executed by artists in England on the occasion of the 40th Anniversary of the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg with an accompanying note of transmittal indicating that this was the first miniature print executed; program for the opening event on Sept, 11, 2003; 40th Anniversary souvenir bookmark; 40th Anniversary decal for windows, bumpers, binders; 40th Anniversary Polo Shirt; memo in re UPG Staff Assoc. fundraising program, i.e., selling polo and long sleeve denim shirts with an embroidered anniversary logo with proceeds going towards the purchase and installation of a flagpole at the athletic fields flag plaza; memo in re the creation of a banner by the UPG Quilters to commemorate the 40th anniversary of the campus.
    Newspaper Clippings Contains: Greensburg Tribune Review insert of 9/9/03, "University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg: 40th, 1963-2003, Celebrating 40 Years With You"; copy of the [UPG] Insider, v. 11 #1, 9/18/03; copy of PITT Chronicle, v. 4 #24, 9/22/03 p3; copy of University Times, v.36 #7, 11/20/03, p4-5; various clippings, 8/28/03-4/5/04.
    Power Point Presentation by President Cassell, 9/11/03 (CD-Rom and printed copy of narrative).
    Programs Contains: opening ceremony program, UPG 40th Anniversary, 9/11/03; program for the UPG vs. UPB [University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg vs. University of Pittsburgh at Bradford] women's and men's basketball 40th anniversary game for the Rose Trophy, 1/31/04, Petersen Event Center (Oakland Campus).
    - 40th Anniversary, 2003 (File-cabinet 1, Drawer 1, Box 2, Drawer 2, Box 3, Box 4, Museum-cabinet 4, Shelf 12)
  - 45th Anniversary, 2008; 3.
    Booklet, "Anniversary Planner" Celebrating 45 Years Pitt-Greensburg 1963-2008
    Program, "La Cultura 2008-09 Lecture Series"; news clippings; poster for Fall theater production of "An Evening of One-Acts".
    - 45th Anniversary, 2008 (File-cabinet 1, Drawer 2, Box 4)
  - 50th Anniversary, 2013; 4.
    Citation. 50th Anniversary Citation. "Congress of the United States House of Representatives In Recognition of the 50th Anniversary of the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg, June 8, 2013." Tim Murphy, Member of Congress, 18th Congressional District.
    Document. [Congratulations]. Senate of Pennsylvania. In the Senate, June 30, 2012, "...upon the celebration of its [University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg] golden anniversary, which it will celebrate from October 6, 2012 to May 4, 2013...".
    Document. Hempfield Township Board of Supervisors. Proclamation. [Proclamation of Congratulations and Appreciation [on the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg celebrating its 50 year anniversary].
    Miscellanea:
    "Celebrating 50 Years of Pitt Greensburg. Investing in the Future. 1963-2013." Contents: Downloaded from the UPG campus website: "50 Changes in 50 Years"; "50 Faces of Pitt-Greensburg"; "Share Your Pitt-Greensburg Memory"; "50th Anniversary Kickoff Celebration". File also contains: Brochure: "[Pitt-Greensburg's] Thoroughbred Horse Trip May 23-34, 2013."; newspaper story, "At 50, Pitt-Greensburg reflects on Milestones," by Shannon M. Nass, Pittsburgh Post Gazette, 3/28/13 p.EZ-1, EZ-5; Program of Palace Theater performance of ELEANOR April 4-5, 2013; University Times (v. 46 #3, 9/26/13) article, Turning 50, Three Pitt regionals celebrate the past & contemplate the future." See also: issues of INTERCOM (RG50 Ser.: Serials. INTERCOM 2012/2013); RG52 and qRG52 Ser.: UPG Theater Dept: Productions Season 2012/13 ELEANOR.
    - 50th Anniversary, 2013 (File-cabinet 1, Drawer 3, Box 5)
- Capital Fund Campaign [Variant Names: Greensburg Campus Development Fund; Development Fund], 1965-2007; IV.
  - Greensburg Campus Development Fund, 1965; 1.
    1965 Greensburg Campus Development Fund, University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg. Albert B. Smith, President, Univ. of Pittsburgh at Greensburg.
    University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg Development Fund Campaign. Final Report transmitted by Jack Cunningham, Ketchum, Incorporated, Campaign Director, to Dr. Albert Smith, July 1, 1965, President of the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg. Includes: Campaign Director's Report; Report of the Associate Director Publicity and Public Information; memorandum, "The Collection Plan"; memorandum, "Suggested Follow-Up Program"; Campaign Timetable; Memorials Reserved; Statistic Section--Campaign Report; Expense Summary; Campaign Organization. Additional documents include: Transmittals; Advance Gifts--Latrobe; Corporations; Primary Gifts; Supporting Gifts; Foundations; Master Projects Assignments Forms. Also contains miscellaneous materials: University of Pittsburgh press release of 10/10/62, "Pitt to Establish College Campus at Greensburg" and press release of 10/31/62, "Pitt Names President of New Greensburg Campus"; minutes of Advisory Board, Univ. of Pittsburgh at Greensburg, 3/29/66 with Acting Chancellor Kurtzman in attendance with following subjects, inter alia: announcement by Dr. Kurtzman that Dr. Geise, for reasons of health, asked to be relieved of his duties as Vice Chancellor for Regional Programs and that the regional campuses would be under Vice Chancellor Charles Peake and that Richard Rose would continue to serve as Coordinator of Regional Campuses; discussion of negotiations with the state about "state relatedness" for Pitt and the implications of "state relatedness", e.g., on fund raising.
    - Greensburg Campus Development Fund, 1965 (File-cabinet 1, Drawer 2, Box 6)
  - Greensburg Campus Development Fund. Addendum, 1960s-1980s; 2.
    Bulk covers period 1960's-1970's + two referring items from 1980's.
    Includes: letters, press releases, memoranda
    Subjects: contributions, grant received by UPG, recommended capital budgets, future building projects, interest payments, capital fund summaries, operations summaries (indebtedness)
    - Greensburg Campus Development Fund. Addendum., 1960s-1980s (File-cabinet 1, Drawer 2, Box 6)
  - Building For The Future, 1988; 3.
    George F. Chambers, President, University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg.
    Brochure: Building for the Future [1987] [Brochure accompanied by copy of an explanatory letter from John A. Robertshaw, Jr. together with a campaign pledge card.]
    Draft Documents: "University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg, Building for the Future Campaign, Campaign Organization and Procedures. [Enclosure 1, 9/10/87]". "The Case for the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg, Building for the Future. [Enclosure 2]". "Campaign Summary" "Development Campaign, Capital Construction Program" "Greensburg Fact Sheet(s)" "Twenty-Five Years of Service"
    Map Photocopy of campus map showing existing and proposed buildings, facilities.
    - Building For The Future, 1988 (File-cabinet 1, Drawer 2, Box 6)
  - Investing in Excellence, 2000-2007; 4.
    Dr. Frank Cassell, President, University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg.
    See also: RG52 Ser.: Annual Fund; RG52 'Partners in Excellence' Annual Internal Campaign
    See also: RG02.4 Ser.: PowerPoint Presentation to the University of Pittsburgh Board of Trustees. Feb. 18, 1999.
    - Investing in Excellence, 2000-2007 (File-cabinet 1, Drawer 2, Box 6)
- Certificates [Awards], 1990-2007; V.
  The Flag of the United States of America. This is to certify that the accompanying flag
  [flag not deposited in the UPG Archives, faz, 12/17/99] was flown over the United States
  Capitol on February 20, 1990 at the request of the Honorable John P. Murtha, Member of
  Congress. This flag was flown for the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg. George M. White, FAIA,
  Architect of the Capitol.
  Certificate of Appreciation. This certificate is awarded to University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg for your continued support of the American Red Cross. American Red Cross, Westmoreland County Chapter. 11-01-01. Donna Pacella, Executive Director. Ben Jones, Chapter Chairman.
  Greensburg Salem Elementary Schools Certificate of Participation. The University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg has been awarded this certificate for participating in Read for Lifelong Learning and Lunch Buddies held at Amos K. Hutchinson Elementary School. This certificate is awarded this 12th day of April, 2002. Mrs. Hricenak, teacher. Mr. Mansfield, Principal.
  Certificate of Appreciation. Awarded to University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg Library in recognition of participation in events celebrating the 250th Anniversary of General Braddock's 1753 March through Westmoreland County. With your assistance, Westmoreland Heritage was able to increase awareness of and appreciation for this important period in the early history of Westmoreland County. Thomas W. Headley, Executive Director, Westmoreland Heritage. Dr. Frank A. Cassell, Chairman, Westmoreland Heritage.
  [AWARD] "Quest for the Best 2007" Gold Award presented to University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg Category: College/University by the readers of the Tribune-Review, Trib Total Media.
  [Certificate] "Above and Beyond" 2001 Leadership Firm Recognition, "In Recognition of Superior Performance in the Development of Leadership Giving Honoring Companies with Three or More Leadership Givers" Presented to University of Pittsburgh-Greensburg. United Way of Westmoreland County.
  - Certificates [Awards], 1990-2007 (File-cabinet 1, Drawer 2, Box 7)
- Directories, 1963-2018; VI.
  - Pitt Greensburg Campus Telephone Directory, 1988-2018; 1.
    1988: February, April 8 1990: January 1991: Spring, Fall 1992: Spring, Fall 1993: Spring, Fall 1994: Spring, Fall 1995: Spring, Summer, Fall 1996: Spring, Summer, Fall 1997: Spring, Summer, Fall 1998: Spring, Summer, Fall 1999: Spring (99.2), Summer (99.3), Fall (00.1) 2000: Spring (00.2), Summer (00.3), Fall (01.1) 2001: Spring (01.2), Summer (01.3), Fall (02.1) 2002: Spring (02.2), Fall (03.1) 2003: Spring (03.2), Summer (03.3), Fall (04.1) 2004: Spring (04.2), Fall (05.1) 2005: [Spring] (05.2), Fall (06.1) 2006: Fall (2071) 2007: Fall (2081) 2008: Spring (2084), Fall (2091) 2009: Fall (2101) 2010: Fall (2111) 2011: Fall (2121) 2012: Fall (2131) 2013: Spring (2134) 2013: Fall (2141) 2014: none issued 2015: Spring 2015 (Revisted 2/16/15; 3/22/15) 2015: Revised 7/9/15, 9/24/15 2016: Revised 1/20/16 2017: Revised 2/1/17 2017: as of 4/7/2017 2017: as of 6/13/2017 2018: as of 1/12/2018 2018: as of 4/2/2018 2018: as of 10/18/2018 2018: as of 11/28/2018 2019: as of 10/09/2019
    - Pitt Greensburg Campus Telephone Directory, 1988-2018 (File-cabinet 1, Drawer 2, Box 7)
  - Directory (Telephone/Addresses) Administration, Faculty, Staff, 1994-1998; 2.
    Includes name of employee, name of spouse, home address, campus address, home telephone, campus telephone, e-mail address.List does not include names of temporary full-time and part-time employees.
    1994, January 1995, Feb. 1996, Feb. 1 1996, December 4 1997, Oct. 20 1998, January, October
    - Directory (Telephone/Addresses) Administration, Faculty, Staff, 1994-1998 (File-cabinet 1, Drawer 2, Box 7)
  - Faculty/Staff Directory. Fall., 1963; 3.
    [Print copy from UPG Archives RG07 Registrar Ser.: Class Schedules [Microform Edition], Fall, 1963-1970-71.]
    - Faculty/Staff Directory. Fall., 1963 (File-cabinet 1, Drawer 2, Box 7)
  - Faculty/Staff Directory [University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg], 1999-2007; 4.
    First issued in this format for 1999-2000.Gives: Academic Calendar; Security and Emergency Procedures; Reserving Rooms; Key Facilities and Services with Hours; Athletic Dept. Personnel; Voice Mail System Guide; Mulberry Quick Start Guide; Profile and History of UPG; Map of Campus Facilities; Organization (University of Pittsburgh; UPG President's Staff; UPG Faculty Division Chairperson; UPG Advisory Board, University Office and Department Listings; University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg Governance; Faculty and Staff Alphabetical Listings; Emeritus Faculty; Anti Discrimination Statement.
    Holdings: 1999-2000 2000-2001 2001-2002 2002-2003 2003-2004 2004-2005 2005-2006 2006-2007 [last published in this form]
    Succeeded in 2008 by Phone Directory [Directory of Faculty and Staff; Campus Directory] n.b.: For current listing for UPG Administration, Academic Affairs (Full-Time Faculty, Part-Time Faculty, UPG Advisory Board, See: http://www. bulletins.pitt.edu/greensburg/contacts.html//Anchor-DIR... [faz 5/20/14]
    - Faculty/Staff Directory [University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg], 1999-2007 (File-cabinet 1, Drawer 2, Box 7)
  - Phone Directory [Directory of Faculty and Staff; Campus Directory], 2008; 5.
    2008 [as of June 10, 2008]
    2091 Campus Directory [as of November 14, 2008]
    - Phone Directory [Directory of Faculty and Staff; Campus Directory], 2008 (File-cabinet 1, Drawer 2, Box 7)
- Handbooks, 1993-1994; VII.
  University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg Faculty/Staff Handbook, 1993. [The UPG Information Handbook for Faculty and Staff, 1993-1994.]
  - Handbooks, 1993-1994 (File-cabinet 1, Drawer 2, Box 7)
- Policy Statements, 1995-2017; VIII.